THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
字幕：破烂熊
校对、调轴、格式化：Obster-Y@github
仅供交流  严禁商用
节约运动
看过了?
You've read it?
看了
I've read it.
看这个了吗?
Have you read this?
他看了
He's read it.
我念给你听
Let me read it to you!
我们看过了
We've read it.
“把Jim·Hacker辞退”
"Let's get rid of Jim Hacker",
特别调查员John·Pilgrim撰稿
by John Pilgrim special investigator.
Jim·Hacker议员阁下
The Right Honourable Jim Jacker MP,
曾承诺履行政府提出的
promised to carry out the government's plans
精简行政机构的计划
to slim down the Civil Service, listen,
清除来自白厅及市政厅
to wipe out the interference from the WhiteHall and
好事之人的干扰
Town Hall busybodies.
但有多少人意识到 调查表明毫无进展
But how many people realise that the detectives want a example
在国内税收部门工作的人
more people serve in the Inland Revenue
甚至比在皇家海军服役的人还多?
than the Royal Navy?
-真的吗?  -确有其事 大臣
- Is it true? - I believe it is, Minister.
“也许政府认为
"Perhaps the government thinks
-征税才是最佳的国防”  -还挺幽默的
- that a tax is the best form of defence". - Oh that's rather witty.
-这段你看过了吗?  -看过了
- And have you read this bit? - I have read it.
“我发现至少有四个部门
"I have discovered that no less than four ministries
负责检查同一种陆军制服的供给情况
check the supply of the same army uniforms.
国防部检查是否收到了所订货物
The Ministry Defence checks to see they get what they ordered.
而工业部检查
But the Department of Industry
这些服装是否
checks to see they have been manufactured
按照政府规定的标准生产
according to government regulations.
财政部检查款项 而Jim·Hacker那伙人
The Treasury checks the bills. And Jim Hacker's mob
只是监督其他所有人
just checks up on everyone else.
Jim·Hacker本人就是白厅冗员繁多
Jim Hacker is the most obvious case
最明显的例子
of overmanning in WhiteHall.
让我们首先把他辞退 至少可以省下一份薪水”
Let's start by getting rid of him and save at least one salary".
Frank 干吗要念给我听 我告诉你我看过了
Frank, why did you read me that? I told you I'd read it.
因为我是你的政治顾问
Because I'm your political advisor.
你有没有意识到 这在政治上会有多大的破坏性
Do you realise how politically damaging for you.
早上好 大臣
Good morning, Minister.
你看了吗?
Have you read this?
看了! 看了! 看了!
Yes! Yes! Yes!
我看过了! 我看过了
I have read it! I have read it,
你看过了 他也看过了
You have read it, he has read it!
我们都他妈看过了
We have all bloody read it,
我说得还不清楚吗?
do I make myself clear?
再清楚不过了 大臣
Abundantly, Minister.
很抱歉 坐
I'm sorry. Sit down.
Humphrey 我们必须精简公务员
Humphrey, we have got to slim down the Civil Service.
我们部门里有多少人?
Howmany people have we got in this department?
这个部门吗? 哦 我们部很小的
This department? Oh, we're very small.
小? 有多小?
Small? How small?
-不知道...  -2千人?
- I don't know... - 2,000?
3千?
3,000?
我想 大概2万3千人吧 大臣
about 23,000 I think, Minister.
2万3千人?
23,000?
在行政部?
In the Department of Administrative Affairs?
这2万3千人都在管理其他行政人员?
23,000 people just administering other administrators?
我们得研究一下体制和工作方法 看看哪些是冗员
We'll have to do a study to see who we can get rid of.
-去年我们倒是研究过 大臣阁下  -结果呢?
- We did one of those last year, minister. - And?
结果表明我们还需要再增加五百人
It transpired we needed another 500 people.
不过 大臣阁下 我们可以关闭
However minister, we could always close
你那个政府部门监察办公室
your Bureaucratic Watchdog Office.
这可不行 这才刚刚成立
No, you don't. The office just opened.
这可是我上任以来做的唯一事情
It's the one thing I've done since I got here.
随便您 大臣 不过那早已为人诟病
But as you wish minster, it has been criticised
-被称作好事者的信箱  -我知道
- as a trouble makers' letterbox. - I know.
不过 在选民中倒很受欢迎 Humphrey
It's very popular with the voters Humphrey
这能让我们找到方法
This is a chance to help us find ways
杜绝浪费政府资金
to stop wasting government money.
但是公众对如何挥霍
But public doesn't know anthing about wasting
公家的钱财可是一窍不通 我们才是专家
government money. We are the experts.
我可不是这个意思
That's not what I meant.
总之 监察办公室要保留下来
Well, the Bureaucratic Watchdog Office stays.
这样的话 我一时也想不出什么建议了
Well, offhand I can't think of what else to suggest.
你是在认真地跟我说
Are you seriously telling me that
我们没有办法精简人员吗?
there is no way we can cut down?
我想我们可以裁掉一两个端茶小姐
I suppose we could lose one or two of the tea ladies.
别闹了 Humphrey
Oh, Humphrey,
我确实希望你能端正下态度
I do wish you'd take this seriously.
端茶小姐! 我要的是事实
Tea ladies! I want the facts.
我要知道谁在这儿工作 都干些什么工作
I want to know who works here, what they do,
我们有哪些楼 里面的人都在干什么
what buildings we have, what goes on in them.
完整的记录
And complete record.
然后就能知道哪儿该节省开支
Then we'll know where to cut costs,
裁减人员 简化程序了
cut staff, cut procedures...
大臣 行政部门
The Civil Service, Minister,
就是为了贯彻议会颁布的法律而存在的
exists to implement legislation enacted by Parliament.
只要议会还在立法
As long as Parliament continues to legislate,
行政机构...
the Civil Service...
不过 我完全理解您的要求 大臣
However, I am fully seized of your requirements, minister.
请允许我这就去让轮子转起来
and if you excuse me I'll go and set the wheels in motion.
谢谢
Thank you.
早上好 Weasel先生
Good morning, Mr. Weasel.
Weisel
Weisel.
你知道吗 一个西北地区区长
Did you know that a northwest Regional Controller
仅在他的区域就削减了三千两百万英镑的开支
has achieved cuts of 32 million pounds in his region alone?
而行政机构却把这消息给压了下去
And that the Civil Service is suppressing the whole story?
-真的吗?  -要是真的 就太震惊了
- Is it true? - Well if it is, I'm aghast!
为什么要压制消息?
Why does it suppress news?
因为连他都做得到的话 那别人也不得不节约了
Because if he can save money, everyone else will have to do it.
你何不调查一下
Why don't you look into it,
做个雪貂 四处打探(ferret本意雪貂，引申为打探)
have a bit of a ferret around?
你觉得我可以吗?
Do you think I could?
我觉得主意不错
I think that's a very good idea,
-雪貂 哦不对 Wea…Weisel先生  -嘿！
- Mr. Ferret, er, Weasel. - Hey!
他告诉你是三千二百万英镑?
He told you 32 million pounds?
-是的 Humphrey爵士  -太震惊了
- Yes, Sir Humphrey. - I'm aghast!
我也是
So was I.
我们居然不知道 太不可思议了
It's incredible we didn't know about it.
我早就知道了
I knew about it.
那你为什么震惊?
Then why are you aghast?
我震惊是因为消息泄漏了
I'm aghast that it got out.
明年或许财政部不会给我们那么多钱了
We might get less money from the Treasury next year.
哦 五点半已经过了 来杯雪利酒?
Oh, it's after half past five. Sherry?
呃 嗯 好的 谢谢
Oh, er, yes. Thank you.
你看起来还是很担心 Bernard
You still look worried, Bernard.
嗯 是的
Well... yes.
我的意思是 当然我们想要省钱
I mean, surely we want to save money.
Bernard 你很清楚
Bernard, You know perfectly well
政府部门必定要有
there has to be some way
某种衡量其成就的方法
to measure success in the Civil Service.
英国利兰公司以他们的利润
British Leyland measure their success
来衡量成就
by the size of their profits,
或者 更准确地说
or, to be more accurate,
他们是以自己的损失来衡量失败
they measure their failure by the size of their losses.
我们没有利润 也没有损失
We don't have profits and losses.
我们的成就是靠
We have to measure our success
雇员人数和预算的多少来衡量的
by the size of our staff and our budget.
明白地说 Bernard
By definition, Bernard,
庞大的部门比小部门更有成就
a big department is more successful than a small one.
你是不是说那名西北地区区长
Are you saying that the northwest Regional Controller
省下那么多钱是在做傻事?
boobed by saving so much money?
哦 当然 谁也没让他这么做
Well, of course. Nobody asked him to.
要是人人都如此
Suppose everybody did it!
要是所有人都开始
Suppose everyone went around saving money
不负责任地到处省钱
irresponsibly all over the place.
大臣正有此意 不是吗?
That's what the Minister wants, isn't it?
坐下 Bernard
Do sit down, Bernard.
大臣们就像走马灯更换无常
Ministers come and Ministers go.
任何部门的大臣
The average Minister lasts less
平均任期都不到十一个月
than 11 months in any department.
听着 Bernard 我们责无旁贷地
You see, Bernard, it is our duty
应协助大臣争取部门经费
to assist the Minister to fight for the Department's money
即便他自己担惊受怕
despite his own panic reactions.
你是说帮他克服恐慌
You mean help him overcome his panic.
不 不 不
No. No. No.
我们任他惊慌失措
No, we must let him panic.
政治家乐意惊惶失措 他们需要活动
Politicians like to panic. They need activity.
以此代替成就
It's their substitute for achievement.
我们必须确保一切照旧
We must just ensure that it doesn't change anything.
可他们是民众的代表
But even so they are the people's representatives,
是民主选举的结果
democratically chosen.
议员并非人民的选择
MP's aren't chosen by the people,
而是其所在地党派决定的
they are chosen by their local party.
是由35个穿着邋遢雨衣的男人
35 men in grubby raincoats
或是35个戴着愚蠢礼帽的女人
or 35 women in silly hats.
可内阁成员来自他们中最优秀的人
And the government are selected from the best of them.
Bernard
Bernard,
下院议员仅有630位
there are only 630 MP's.
一个党派超过300名席位便组成内阁
If one party has just over 300 it forms a government.
这300人中 有100名又老又蠢
Of that 300, one hundred are too old and too silly,
还有100名又稚又嫩
one hundred too young and too callow
剩下的大约100名下院议员
which leaves just about a hundred MP's
便填上了100个政府职务
to fill 100 governmental posts.
根本无从挑选
There's no choice at all.
他们未经甄别 未受训练
They've had no selection, no training.
我们不得不为他们代劳
We have to do the job for them.
但节省3千2百万开支的事
But how can we explain saving 32 million pounds
如何向大臣解释?
to the Minister?
我们可以声称
Well, We can explain they've changed
西北的账目体系有了改变
their accounting systems in the northwest.
或者各区的管辖范围经过重新划分
Or that they've redrawn the regional boundaries
现在的数据已经没有意义了
so that the current figures aren't operable.
一切皆有可能
There are all sorts of possibilities.
明白了
I see.
有益的交谈 Bernard
Useful chat, Bernard,
记住这从未发生过
good job it never took place.
是的 当然没有
Yes. Yes. Of course.
我们的朋友Weasel上哪去了?
So what else is our friend Weasel up to?
他在当雪貂
Oh, he's ferretting.
当雪貂? 哪儿?
Ferretting? Where?
四处打探
It's a roving brief.
看来我们不得不给侦查员安排辆政府用车了
Then we shall have to provide Rover with a government car.
便于了解他在哪儿打洞了
So that we'll know where he's digging.
你…
How...
你是如何和谐你的大臣的 小汉?
how are you getting on with your Minister, Humpy?
还没把那节约的事控制住?
Got this economising nonsense under control?
是的 控制住了 巨人 或多或少
Yes, I think so, Jumbo... more or less.
“或多或少”什么意思?
What do you mean more or less?
好吧 既是又不是
Well... yes and no.
大概与所有其他的政府节约一样吧?
Presumably it's like all the other government economy drives?
三天的新闻发布 三周的内阁备忘录
Three days of press releases, three weeks of ministerial's memos,
中东发生危机 一切恢复正常?
a crisis in the Middle East and back to normal again?
这次稍有不同
Well this one's slightly different.
他想他是要把
I'm afraid He's beginning to see
裁员视为其首要任务了
slimming down the Service as his main task.
该死的 我们无须瘦身!
Dammit, we don't need slimming!
我想你或许应该
I think you might have to conduct
再来一个“自讨苦吃行动”
another Operation Hair Shirt.
自讨苦吃行动
Operation Hair Shirt.
明智的主意
What a good idea.
引领他感受痛苦的个人节约
Guide him towards painful personal economies.
就是这样 你知道
Yes, you know.
“节约应从‘我’做起 大臣阁下”
"Economy begins at home, Minister".
“要树立表率 大臣阁下”
"Set an example, Minister".
“我们必须身体力行才能令人信服 大臣阁下”
"Can't expect others to do what we can't do ourselves, Minister".
对极了 这正是他需要的 自我否定
Yes, yes. Just what he needs, self denial.
了不起
Splendid.
好 第3项 节约运动
Right. Item 3. The economy drive.
有关我们的铺张浪费 Frank 提供了
Frank has come up with some really startling indications
一些让人震惊的信息
of wastage in our very midst.
他核实过了?
Has he confirmed?
我想我揭露的事实准会让你大吃一惊的
And I think you gonna be pretty surprised of what I uncovered
我得说 Humphrey
And I must say Hamphrey
这些事实看来是对
These facts are a frightening indictment
官僚作风与自我放纵的可怕谴责
of bureaucratic sloppiness and self indulgence.
天哪 天哪
Dear, yeah.
但如你所见
But as you'll see,
这倒是给我们提供了巨大的空间
they do give us enormous scope
来大刀阔斧地开展节约运动
for some really dramatic economies.
令人期待!
Good show!
两份报告 一份关于人力资源 一份办公楼
Two files, one on manpower, one on buildings.
从办公楼开始吧
Let's start with the buildings.
Chadwick大厦 西Audley街
Chadwick House, West Audley Street.
巨大的建筑 但办公的人却寥寥无几
A huge building only a handful of people working there.
是啊 20人
Yes, 20...
抱歉 我恰好清楚Chadwick大厦的情况
I'm so sorry. I do happen to know about Chadwick House.
你了解些什么?
What do you know?
很显然并未充分利用
It's obviously underused at the most,
但它已被指定为
but it's the destinite office
新成立的环境署办公楼
for the new Commission for the Environment.
我们还说不准它是否
And we're actually wondering
足够容纳所有的工作人员
if it's going to be big enough for all the staff.
好吧
O.K.
那么位于Walthamstow的Ladysmith大厦呢?
What about Ladysmith Buildings, Walthamstow.
-那可是完全空着  -理应如此
- Apparently that's empty. - Of course.
你的“理应如此”的意思是?
What do you mean, of course?
出于安全考虑 大臣 我不能多言
Security, minister. I can say no more.
你是指军情六处?
Do you mean MI6?
这又是什么意思?
What's that supposed to mean?
我们不承认有军情六处这回事
We do not admit that MI6 exists.
谁不知道它的存在
Everybody knows it exists.
即便如此 我们不能承认
Nevertheless, we do not admit it.
这桌子旁坐着的人并非都是经过检疫的
Not everyone round this table has been vetted.
对猫才用“检疫”这个词吧
I thought that was something you do cats.
确实如此 对“雪貂”就不用 大臣阁下
Yes, indeed. But not ferrets, Minister.
Ladysmith大厦是最高机密
Ladysmith House is top secret.
Walthamstow上七层的大厦怎么会是最高机密?
How can a seven-storey building in Walthamstow to be top secret?
有志者事竟成
Where there's a will there's a way.
那Wellington大厦和Westminster旧厅呢?
What about Wellington House and Westminster Old Hall?
Wellington大厦 位于Hyde公园大道
Wellington House, Hyde Park Road,
价值七百五十万英镑
estimated value 7.5 million pounds.
Westminster旧厅 位于Sackville广场
Westminster Old Hall, Sackville Square,
价值一千一百万英镑
estimated value 11 million pounds.
两幢办公楼里的员工都不多
Each building with a tiny staff,
却都摆满了档案柜
and both filled apparently entirely with filing cabinets.
请问这些估价的根据是?
May I ask the source of these valuations?
办公用房的市价
Going rate for office property in the end.
但它们没一个能卖到这个现行价格
But neither of these properties would fetch the going rate.
为什么不能?
Why not?
Wellington大厦既没有防火梯 也没有防火门
Wellington House has no fire escape or fire doors
而大厦的构造也不容改建
and the fabric of building wouldn't stand the alteration.
不能当作办公楼
so it can't be used as offices.
-那你是如何用上这幢大厦的?  -是啊
- How are you able to use them? - Yeah?
政府办公楼无须防火安全通道
Government buildings do not require fire safety clearance.
为何不用?
Why not?
可能是女王陛下的公仆们
Well, perhaps because Her Majesty's Civil Servants
不易着火吧
are not easily inflamed.
希望如此
I hope it is right.
那Westminster旧厅呢?
What about Westminster Old Hall?
一级保护建筑
Class one Registered Building.
不能改变当前房屋使用人
Can't change current user designation.
好吧 Beaconsfield街上的3到17号大楼呢?
I see. 3 to 17 Beaconsfield Street?
对 是了 该建筑现在有了三层的
Ah, yes. Now that has a three-level
钢筋混凝土地下室
reinforced concrete basement.
这又怎么了?
So?
防范未然
It is there in case.
未然什么?
In case?
要知道 大臣阁下
Well, you know, Minister.
政府应急总部所在地 以防万一
Emergency Government Headquarters, if and when.
万一怎么了?
If and when what?
万一... 你明白的
If and when... you know what.
什么?
What?
你明白的那个万一
If and when you know what.
我不明白 是什么?
I don't know what. What?
什么
What?
你那句“你明白的那个万一”是什么意思?
What do you mean, if and when you know what?
大臣 万一危机来临
Minister, when the chips are down,
局势动荡 吹灯拔蜡…
and the balloons are up and the lights go out...
政府也得有个地方继续运行啊
There has to be somewhere to carry on government,
即便一切都陷入瘫痪
even if everything else stops.
为什么?
Why?
难道国家分崩离析了
The government just stops just because
内阁就该偃旗息鼓吗?
the whole country's been destroyed.
毁于一旦已经够糟了
Annihilation's bad enough,
无政府状态只会雪上加霜
without anarchy to make things even worse.
你以为尚有许多反叛的余孽?
you mean a lot of rebellions cinders?
没错
That's right.
到那时你还指望管理谁?
Who would be there for you to govern?
肯定还会有些普通民众
Well, abound to be some ordinary people around.
那中央户籍登记处的那幢楼呢?
What about central registry?
没有建筑许可
No planning permission.
他怎么什么都知道?
How did he know all these?
你早就知道我去哪儿了?
You knew where I'd been.
我们当然知道他何去何从
Obviously we knew where he'd been.
难不成他本该暗中打探吗?
Why, was he supposed to be spying?
我们信奉公开调查 不是吗?
We do believe in open enquiries, don't we?
我们看看人力资源方面
Let us turn to manpower.
对 我们看看
Yes, let's!
在Sunderland就有90名公务员
Aparently there are 90 Civil Servants
明显在重复白厅这儿
in Sunderland except the duplicating the work
另外90个人从事的工作
of 90 more here in WhiteHall.
这源于内阁的一项决定
That stems from a Cabinet decision,
-为东北地区创造就业机会  -把这些人裁了吧
- job creation in the northeast. - Well let's get rid of them.
对 一下子就裁掉了90名公务员
Yes, we'd get rid of 90 Civil Servants at a stroke.
-是啊 或是一下子就引起了一场罢工  -对 什么?
- Yes, or indeed, at a strike. - Yes. What?
个人而言 我完全
Well, personally I would be whole heartily
赞成这个行动 大臣阁下
in favour of such a move, minister.
这会是一场辉煌的节约运动
It would be a splendid economy.
在一个萧条的边缘选区裁员
And show great political courage to sack staff
会展现出极大的政治魄力
in depressed marginal constituencies.
我就是不信
I just don't believe it that
没有可节约之处 浪费明明随处可见
There is nowhere we can cut down. I see waste everywhere.
我同意您的话 大臣阁下
Well I agree with you, Minister.
确有可节约之处
There's certain diseconomy
好吧 哪儿?
Well, where?
我有时会觉得恰恰是
Well. I sometimes feel that the very way
我们的行事排场太过奢侈
we do things is on too lavish a scale.
您知道 汽车 办公器材
You know, cars, furnishings...
娱乐设备 私人办公人员 复印机…
entertainments, private office staff, duplicating machines...
对 对 对 好极了
Yes. Yes. Yes. Fine. Yes.
我们就从这下手 这可太妙了
That's where we'll start. Magnificent.
-不过 这里还有个问题  -我就知道
- Yes, unfortunely there is a difficulty. - I knew it!
是啊 如果上头的人还继续享受
Yes, it does cause profound resentment
各种便利和舒适
if those at the top continue to enjoy
却不让下面的人分享
the comforts, the conveniences,
势必会引起强烈的不满
they withdraw from those below them,
更不必说公众舆论导致的可怕后果
not to mention the deeply damaging publicity...
你是说我和你应该…
You mean you and I should...
以身作则?
Set a personal example?
节约应从“我”做起?
Economy begins at home?
我们必须身体力行
We can't expect others to do
才能令人信服 不是吗?
what we don't do ourselves, can we?
靠这个好像省不出多少吧?
Does it really save all that much?
当然不会直接省下来
Well, not directly, no.
但对整个政府部门的模范作用将不可限量
but as an example to the whole public service incalculable.
好吧 不知道...
Well, I don't know...
你想 Jim 这会产生巨大的公众效应
You know, Jim, there'd be a lot of great publicity in it:
“大臣指明了方向”
"The Minister shows the way".
“清廉的内阁”
"Slimline Government".
“哈克作出了表率”
"Hacker sets an example".
Jim号召“节约”
"Save it" says Jim.
对 对 就这样
Yes. Yes, that's it.
好极了 我们从何开始?
Great, where do we start?
-把灯...  -抱歉 你睡了?
- Turn the... - Sorry. Were you asleep?
是的
Yes.
我错过了火车
I missed my train.
不得不一路步行到Euston
Had to walk all the way to Euston.
你的那辆公家司机开的车呢?
What happen to the chauffeur driven car?
削减掉了
Got rid of it.
为什么?
Why?
连司机一起退掉了
Got rid of all the chauffeur, too.
所有豪华的办公家具
and all that grand office furniture,
藏酒 我私人办公室的大半人员
drinks cabinet, half the staff in my private office.
-你被开除了  -没有 没有
- You've been sacked. - No, no...
-那是为何?  -这叫节约运动
- Then why? - It's an economy drive.
我在作表率
I'm setting an example.
没有奢侈品 没有虚架子 没有特权
No luxuries, no frills, no privileges...
你疯了
You're mad...
你做了20年后座议员 一直抱怨缺东少西
For 20 years you've complained that as a backbencher you had no facilities.
现在一应俱全 你又统统放弃
Now you have been given them and you are throwing them away.
你20年来一直想有所成就
20 years you've wanted to be a success.
如果还没失败来得舒适 这又是何苦呢?
Why did you want it, if it brings no greater comfort than failure?
亲爱的 你不懂政治 对吧?
Honey you don't really understand politics to you.
长此以往 将会给我更大的权利
This way's gonna bring me much more power in the end.
说的不错 亲爱的 你以后当上首相
Yeah, darling. And how are you going to travel
打算以什么代步?
when you are Prime Minister.
搭便车?
Hitch hike?
Bernard 来帮我整理日志
Bernard coming here for a diary cession…
好的 大臣 我把这一打好就来
Yeah, Minister. As soon as I've done this typing.
你不能让…
Can't you get…
真得不行 相当紧急
Not really, it's rather urgent.
裁员后 这儿就剩我们两个了
And since the cutbacks there's just the two of us.
我不得不打理一切
I have to do everything.
好吧 来我办公室 我必须和你谈谈
Well, come to my office I must talk to you.
-Mandy Mandy  -什么事?
- Mandy! Mandy! - Yes?
W键在哪儿?
Where's W?
左上角
Top left.
Bernard 进来!
Bernard! Come in here!
马上
Now!
Bernard 我们必须如约而至
Bernard, we got to get these to my appointment.
我被请了又请 现在还是晚了一个半小时
I was double booked and is half an hours' late for that thing.
是什么 大臣?
What thing is?
商业效率展销会
The Business Efficiency Exhibition!
恕我直言 大臣 但基于…
I do apologise, minister, but what with the, the...
您私人办公的裁员状况
staff economies in your private office,
保持实效十分困难
it is awfully difficult to keep track.
这我也无能为力 下午的日程是
I can't help that. Now what's happening in the afternoon?
我这就去拿日志 大臣
I'll get the diary, minister.
现在不行 亲爱的!
Not now, dear!
现在不行!
Not now!
早上好
Morning
你非得现在打扫吗?
Do you have to do that now?
是的 他们裁掉了夜班工人
Yes. Yes. They've cancelled the night shift.
一些白痴又来什么节约运动了
Some idiot's started another of those economy drives.
-我叫Nellie  -好的 重要的是...
- I'm Nellie. - Good. Well, the point is...
你是谁?
Who are you?
我是大臣
I'm the Minister.
哦 真的?
Oh, really?
真的很高兴见到你
Oh, I'm ever so pleased to meet you.
我投了你的票
I voted for you.
好的 谢谢你
Oh, good. Thank you.
叫我Nellie就行
You can call me Nellie.
谢谢
Thank you.
-我怎么称呼你?  -Jim
- What do I call you? - Er... Jim.
这是日志 大臣阁下
Here's the diary, Minister.
好的 可以关掉它吗 亲爱的?
Right. Turn that off, would you, dear?
关掉 Nellie!
Turn it... Nellie!
什么?
What?
能让我们单独谈谈吗 这是机密
Would you excuse us? This is confidential.
你知道我得工作 Jim
I've got to get on you know, Jim.
我也一样
So have I.
Jim?
好吧 我不用吸尘器
Well, I won't use the hoover.
我会踮起脚尖 你决不会留意到我
I'll tiptoe, you'll never notice me.
-请出去  -我轻如羽毛
- Go please. - I'm light as a feather.
出去 马上
Go! Now!
好吧 行 Jim
All right, All right Jim.
我能领会
I can take a hint.
今天早上只有一位Brough先生 大臣
It's just a Mr.Brough this morning Minister.
我们东北地区的人力计划署主管
our Director of Manpower Planning to the northeast region.
-Brough? -是的 裁员的事
- Brough? - Yes, staff reductions.
-哦 对  -然后直接去上议院
- Oh, yes. - And then straight to the House.
参加7点的质询 答复议员提问
for question time for 7 o'clock division.
8点钟要去法国总理大使馆参加其招待会
at 8 o'clock the French prime minister reception at his Embassy.
好的
Right.
请您原谅 大臣阁下
If you, would you excuse me. Minister
我得把日程交给上议院组织秘书办公室
I must take the schedules down to the Whips' Office.
-Bernard  -大臣阁下 什么事?
- Bernard Bernard... - Yes, Minister?
值得一干 你知道
It is worth it, you know...
正中跨版 三张图片
Centre page spread and three pictures.
是的 我读过了 大臣阁下
Yes, I have read it, Minister.
看我的图片
See this one of me,
拿着纸盒吃干酪卷
with a cheese roll on a cardboard plate?
“Hacker的节俭体制下没有奢侈的午餐”
"No luxury lunches in Hacker's new austerity regime".
“Jim·Hacker今天宣布"节约运动从‘我’做起，
"Economy begins at home" said Jim Hacker today,
他为英国那群头戴圆礼帽
as he set an example to Britain's pampered army
娇生惯养的官僚树立了一个典范”
of bowler hatted bureaucrats".
太棒了 对吗?
Terrific, isn't it?
您已经给我读过了 大臣
Yes you have read it to me already.
-棒极了 对吗?  -是的 大臣阁下
- Great, isn't it? - Oh, Yes, Minister.
节约正在起步(on the beach还有失业之意)
Economise on the beaches...
-打扰了 -什么事?
- Excuse me. - Yes? Yes?
我想见大臣
I would like to see the minister.
你预约了吗?
Do you have an appointment?
我是Ron·Watson
My name is Ron Watson, I'm the General Secretary
行政部门交通工人工会的总书记
of the Union of Civil Service Transport and Associated Government Workers.
好的 Watson先生
Yes, Mr. Watson.
听闻裁员将涉及到我们的会员
We're very disturbed about rumours
我们倍感不安
of could back redundancies affecting our members...
抱歉 Watson先生 您不能见大臣
I'm sorry, Mr. Watson. you can't see the minister.
您必须事先预约
You must have an appointment.
听着 明天打电话给我
like, Phone me tomorrow.
为何不能现在安排?
Why can't I arrange it now?
-很抱歉  -竟然这样!
-I'm sorry. - Oh, really!
好吧 Mandy 安排 Watson先生
Alright, Mandy, make an appointment for Mr. Watson
下周与大臣会面
to see the minister for next week.
下周?
Next week?
你好 Brough先生
Hello... Mr. Brough.
是的 我们正等着Brough先生
Yes, we're expecting Mr. Brough now.
在Euston耽搁了?
When's it due in at Euston?
我们不得不取消今天的会面了
We'll just have to cancel it for today then.
好的 我会向他转达 再见
Yes, yes, I'll tell him. Goodbye.
抱歉让您久等了
Sorry to keep you.
您的预约 定在何时比较方便
Now, about your appointment. When would be convenient...
-会面取消了?  -是的
- The meeting's cancelled then? - Yes.
好啊 那我现在可以见他了吧
Right! So I can see him now.
恐怕不行 你瞧...
Oh no ,I'm afraid not, you see...
你能稍等片刻吗?
Would you excuse me just a moment?
喂? 不 他不在
Yes? No. He's not here.
他去上议院的组织秘书办公室了
He's gone over to the Whips' Office.
您需要转分机吗?
Would you like the extension?
您是…
Ah, Mr...
Brough先生?
Brough?
不是 Brough先生不得不取消会见
No. Mr. Brough's had to cancel the meeting.
我是Ron·Watson 我来...
My name's Ron Watson. I'm...
很高兴您能替他来
I'm glad you could get here instead anyway.
-请坐吧 好吗  -谢谢
- Do sit down, would you. - Oh, thank you.
好吧 恩...
Now, Mr. Er...
Watson
Watson.
Watson先生 在我们开始前
Mr. Watson, Before we start
我必须首先强调一点
there's one thing I must make absolutely clear.
这话一定不能传出去
This must not get out.
要是工会听闻了风声
If the unions were to get to hear of this
准要闹翻天了
all hell would be let loose.
好的
Oh, yes.
当然要进行裁员 不裁减...
Of course there'll be redundancies. You simply...
不裁减冗余的工作人员
You simply can't slim down a giant bureaucracy
如何精简庞大的官僚机构
like this without getting rid of people.
最终 会裁减大量人员
Ultimately, a lot of people.
您为何不首先与工会商量呢?
Won't you be holding discussions with the Unions first?
我们会做做样子 进行磋商
We'll go through the charade of discussions,
但你也知道工会分子们都是些什么人
but you know what Trade Unionists are like;
就会胡搅蛮缠 个个愚蠢透顶
thick as two short planks and bloody minded.
个个如此?
All of them?
几乎都是 天哪 你该有体会
Pretty well. Good lord, you should know.
工会之间只热衷于互挖墙脚
They're interested in poaching each other's members
争上电视 还管不住自己的大嘴巴
and get themselves on the telly and they can't keep their big mouths shut.
司机和交通服务人员怎么办?
What about drivers and transport service staff?
当然是首当其冲
First to go. Good lord.
我们在轿车与司机上浪费了大量财力
We waste a fortuna on cars and drivers.
-而他们个个好逸恶劳  -懂了
- And they're all on the fiddle. - Oh, I see.
其实 我刚才正要解释
Because, as I was trying to explain that,
我不是Brough先生的代表
I'm not Mr. Brough's deputy.
我是行政部门交通工人
I'm the General Secretary of the Union of
以及政府辅助人员工会的总书记
Civil Service Transport and Associated Government Workers.
我
Ah. I...
我来此是为了核实
I came here to check there was no truth in
裁减我成员的谣传是否属实
the rumours of redundancies for my members.
好吧 我...
Well... I... I...
我刚才的意思是...
All I meant was...
哦 天哪
Oh, God.
(行政交通部门罢工)
他逐字引用我的话
He quotes me, word for word:
“当然要进行裁员 大量人员”
"Of course there will be redundancies. Lots!"
万分抱歉 大臣
I'm most terribly sorry.
所有司机都罢工了?
Are all the drivers on strike?
全部响应
100% response.
Bernard 你怎么能眼看着它发生?
How could you allow this to happen?
C.B.E. 大臣阁下
C.B.E., Minister.
什么C.B.E.?
C.B.E.?
无法面面俱到
Can't be everywhere.
当然 在通常情况下...
Of course, in normal circumstances...
好了 好了 知道了 知道了
Yes. Yes. I know, I know.
恕我提醒 您和您夫人8点要出席
Would you mind if I remind you. You and Mrs. Hacker are due
法国大使馆的招待会
at the French Embassy at 8 o'clock.
对 帮我备车好吗?
Oh, yes. Get me the car, will you?
最好先给我夫人打个电话
Oh... Better ring Mrs. Hacker,
让她开我们的车进城
ask her to bring our car into town.
恐怕无法如您所愿 大臣
Well I have to explore the possibility, minister.
您夫人说将它放在修车厂修理了
Mrs. Hacker said she had dropped it off at the garage.
她就不能明天再修吗
She'll have to do that tomorrow.
它可以把我们送至Kensington
It'll get us as far as Kensington anyway.
至少这不成问题
At least there are no problems about that.
Annie 不妙 我们必须步行
Annie, it's no good. We'll have to walk.
你带伞了吗?
Have you got the umbrella?
没 你呢?
No, haven't you?
这下好了
Terrific.
你走错方向了
You're going the wrong way.
没有 我是要回家
I'm not, I'm going home.
Annie 我知道这是什么问题了
Annie! I think I've found what's wrong.
我早就知道了
I know I have!
(法国大使馆)
先生 有何贵干?
Oui, Monsieur?
女皇任命的行政大臣
Her Majesty's Minister for Administrative Affairs.
我的车坏了
My car broke down.
Hacker先生 看来您需要喝点香槟
Mr. Hacker, you look as if you need some champagne.
是的 大量
I do. Lots!
Hacker先生?
Mr. Hacker?
谢了 老兄
Thanks, mate.
黄色小报
Gutter press!
好吧 上面写了什么?
All right, what do they say?
“节约大师香槟酒会后醉卧排水沟”
Mr. Economy falls down in gutter after champagne party".
-老天  -这个好点
- Oh, my God! - This one is better.
“哈克在大使招待会后疲惫不堪 情绪失控”
"Hacker tired and emotional after Embassy reception".
-这叫好点?  -至少有些不同
- Is that better? - It's different.
有没有谁说过任何
Do any of them say anything
“疲惫不堪 情绪失控”之外的话?
other than "tired and emotional"?
William·Hickey说您过度兴奋 大臣阁下
William Hickey said you were overwrought, Minister.
只是“过度兴奋”?
Just "overwrought"?
没有提到醉酒?
Nothing about being drunk?
只有“过度兴奋”
Just "overwrought".
原话其实是“过度兴奋如同笨蛋”
"Overwrought as a newt", actually.
还能有比这更糟吗 还有吗?
It couldn't really be any worse. Could they?
我不想打击您 大臣
I don't want to depress you, minister...
但“泰晤士报”上有个头版报道
but there is just this lead story in The Times.
的确更糟!
It is worse!
“哈克征募了400名新公务员
"Hacker recruit 400 new Civil Servants in,
在其‘节约运动’期间”
quote, 'economy drive'"!
-增加400名公务员?  -大臣 您吩咐用他们
- 400 more Civil Servants? - Minister, You asked for them.
您要求彻底的研究 收集事实和数据
You demanded a complete study and survey, facts and figures.
这些措施得有人手才行
These measures cannot be taken with none people.
你想出了额外的工作 就必须雇佣更多的人手
You create more jobs. More people have to be employed to do it.
这是常识而已
It's common sense.
如果您还坚持落实政府部门监察办公室
If you persist with the Bureaucratic Watchdog Office,
那就至少还要再添400个新职位
there'll be another 400 new jobs there as well.
-我们该如何是好?  -大臣阁下
- What are we going to do? - Well, Minister...
如果我们停止节约运动
If we were to end the economy drive
关闭政府部门监察办公室
and close the Bureaucratic Watchdog Office,
我们可以立即发布新闻通告
we could issue an immediate press announcement
说您砍掉了800个职位
that you'd axed 800 jobs.
现在您只需瞟一眼这份草拟的提案
Now, if you'd care to glance at this draft proposal...
但没人担任过这些职位啊 还没任命过谁呢
But nobody's doing those jobs. Nobody has been recruited yet.
这样节约就更为可观
And even greater economy,
我们还节省了800份裁员费
we've saved 800 redundancy payments as well.
那是造假
That's foully
是谎言 是虚伪 是...
it's cheated, it's dishonest, it's just...
玩数字游戏 蒙蔽他人的耳目而已
cheating with figures, pulling the wool over people's eyes.
-事实上是政府发布的新闻  -好吧
- A Government Press release, in fact. - Fine.
可我们到底该怎样做才能精简行政部门呢?
What do we actually going to do to slim down the Civil Service?
大臣 或许您可以过目一下这份焕然一新的提案
Minister, after you get announce at this entirely fresh proposal.
“提议辞退一二名
"Proposal for the Reduction of the Number of
端茶小姐”
Tea Ladies".